<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The historie of Corah, Dathan, and Abiram, &amp; c Numb. 16. Chap. Applied to the prelacy ministerie and church-assemblies of England. By Mr Iohn Penry, a martyr of Iesus Christ.</title>
            <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09294</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19607</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103159</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838916</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838916</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3307</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09294)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3307)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1213:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The historie of Corah, Dathan, and Abiram, &amp; c Numb. 16. Chap. Applied to the prelacy ministerie and church-assemblies of England. By Mr Iohn Penry, a martyr of Iesus Christ.</title>
                  <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 45, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>R. Schilders?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Middelburg :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Imprinted in the yeare, 1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of the ministrie of the Church of Engl.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Wales --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Wales --  Church history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3307:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3307:1"/>
            <p>THE HISTORIE of Corah, Dathan, and Abiram, &amp;c. <hi>Numb. 16. Chap.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Applied to the Prelacy Miniſterie and Church-aſſemblies of England.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Mr Iohn Penry, a Martyr of Ieſus Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Numb. 16.26.</hi>
               </bibl> And <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake vnto the Congregation, ſaying, Depart, I pray you, from the tents of theſe wicked men, and touch nothing of theirs, least ye periſh in all their ſinnes.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 18.4.</hi>
               </bibl> And I heard another voyce from heaven ſay, Go out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> my people, that ye be not partakers in her ſinnes, and that ye receive not of her plagues.</q>
            <p>Imprinted in the yeare, 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3307:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3307:2"/>
            <head>The Publiſher to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THere comming to my hands (Christian reader) the copie of this treatiſe following, (wherof many copies have paſſed abroad in writing) I thought good (weying well the matter vndertaken, &amp; the partie by whom it was written,) to publiſh the ſame, to the further view of the world. And chiefly for the good of my country: which all true ſubiects are bound by all good meanes to ſeek and advance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſubiect of this book, or matter undertaken, is; A declaration of th'estate of the Church and Ministery of Engl. compared with</hi> Corah, Dathan, Abiram, <hi>their Tents and conſpiracie, against</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, Num. 16. chap. <hi>Which therefore all in whom the true fear of God is, ought carefully to look vnto and examine: For we ſhould trie all things, and keep that which is good. And they who never examine the things charged to be evil and out of order in that Church, must needs be ignorant, whether their estate therin be good or evill. But if they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider that ignorance will not excuſe them, it behooveth all to take know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: whom I hartely wiſh to lay aſide all partialitie, and with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different mindes to weigh things well, trying them by the rule of Gods word, that whatſoever therby is required of them, they may reſolve to do it; although it turne to the loſſe of all worldly pleaſures and preferments: knowing that we have here but a ſhort time, and our God hath reſerved for vs a more induring ſubstance and richer inheritance in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven, if in obedience we ſubmit vnto him, and in faith and pacience do wayt vpon him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Touching the authour, Mr</hi> Iohn Penry <hi>by name; he was a godly man, learned, zealous, &amp; of a most Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cariage &amp; courage: &amp;</hi> (<hi>as he</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">In his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie.</note> 
               <hi>ſaith of himſelf) borne and bred in the mountaines of Wales. And wel known it is, that with all godly care &amp; labour he endeavoured to have the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell preached and planted among his poore countrymen, whoſe caſe he greatly pittied &amp; had compaſsion of, in that they wanted the meanes of ſalvation among them. After all this, God vſing him as a further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument for the more clear manifestation of the truth; he was hardly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated, impriſoned, condemned and executed; &amp; ſo ſuffred Martyrdome
<pb facs="tcp:3307:3"/>for the name of Christ. Being adiudged at the Kings bench by Sir Iohn Popham Knight, Lord cheif Iustice of England, and the reſt of the Iudges there aſſembled, the 25. of the 5. month called May, and executed at Thomas a Waterings by London, the 29. of the ſame month, in the year of our Lord, 1593.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And here let the Reader obſerve, that he was not executed the next day after the iudgement, as it was expected; nor the ſecond, nor third day after; but when men least looked for the ſame, then was he brought forth being at dynner (as I have heard) by a warrant vnder the hands of the</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iohn Whitgift.</note> 
               <hi>Archbiſhop of Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terbury, &amp; of Sir Iohn Puckering Knight, Lord Keeper of the great ſeale, and Sir Iohn Popham aforeſaid, being then Lord chief Iustice of England, and the matter being caried after a cloſe manner, was ſodeinly conveyed to the place of execution; where he was as hastily bereaved of his life, and not ſuffred (though he deſired it) to make de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of his faith towards God, or of his allegiance to her Maiestie. Which m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ner of dealing I thought good to note here by the way, that it might be knowen, and eſteemed of all according as it deſerveth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Furthermore concerning this treatiſe, whether he had finiſhed the whol, or was taken &amp; intercepted, when he had thus far proceeded in it, or what he would further have done about it, I know not. Wherfore if others have more of it, they ſhall do wel to impart it to the world, as I have done this which came to my hands. In the mean time I wiſh all to make good vſe of this part now printed, &amp; they vnto whoſe hands it ſhal come, to enterteyn it as a poore Orphane, who is left as it were Fatherles, by the authours vntimely death, procured by the Prelates: who as vncleane ſpirits like frogges (croaking about Kings Courts) do ſtir vp the Magiſtrates &amp; Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 16.13.14.</note> 
               <hi>to make warre against Gods Saintes. Whereas theſe ſhould rather hearken to that which God ſpeaketh vnto them in his word ſaying,</hi> Be wiſe now therefore, ye Kings: be learned, ye Iudges of the earth: Serve the Lord in feare and rejoyce in trembling: Kiſſe the ſonne, leaſt he be angry, and ye periſh in the way, when his wrath ſhall ſuddenly burne. Bleſſed are all they that truſt in him. <hi>Pſal. 2.10.11.12.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:3307:3"/>
            <head>THE HISTORIE OF CORAH &amp;c. <hi>Numb. 16. chap.</hi> Applied to the Church-aſſemblies of England.</head>
            <p>IT is certayne and apparant that this age cannot in any wiſe brook to have the truth manifeſted &amp; ſpoken in the ſame, except it be by peece meales: So that if ever it were ſaid to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>See not,</hi> &amp; to the prophets, <hi>propheſie not unto us right things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 30.10.</note> 
               <hi>but ſpeak flatteries, propheſie errors, depart out of the way, go aſide out of the path, cauſe the holy one of Jſraell to ceaſſe, fom vs,</hi> the very ſame is now ſayd and ſtood vnto in theſe miſerable dayes: nay thoſe that would be reconed our leaders our eyes our guides, are nowe become the men of Anathoth, and ſay plainelie,<note place="margin">Jer. 11.21.</note> 
               <hi>propheſie not in the name of the Lord, that thou dy not by our hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All eſtates and ſorts of men, high and low, have reaſons why to reiect the truth, why to condemne it, why to tread it vnder foot, and to perſecute the ſame. It is not pleaſant, it is odious, it is offenſive, it is hard, knotty, uncivil, proud, hauty, and what not? It is not pleaſant, becauſe it draweth men into incouvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, it reproveth them to their faces, diſcovereth their evil walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: it in dangereth thoſe that profeſſe the ſame: it carrieth but a mean trayn after it. It is odious and offenſive, for the ſame cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: It is vncivil, proud and haughtie, becauſe it wil correct and reform all: it wil alter ſtates: it regardeth not the years, learning, credite, wiſdome, and eſtimation of thoſe that ſtand againſt it, but goeth about to bring all under foot, and to make them all to ſtoop unto it, or els threatneth to break the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like a potters veſſel: it wil not be ſilent at their commaundement, but contrary wiſe enforceth them to flee her preſence, and not to haue a word to ſpeak that they dare ſtand unto while ſhe is in place.</p>
            <p>Theſe and ſuch like are the cauſes why the truth of God is ſo meanly attended upon, and utterly caſt off among men in our dayes: for what reaſon is there (as men uſually conclude) that thoſe who in the eſtimation of the moſt, are learned, godly, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious &amp;c. ſhould have their practiſes reproved and themſelves condemned as violaters of the Lords morall commandements, ſeing they are eſpecially deemed to urge the obſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of them?</p>
            <p>As an anſwer to all theſe frivolous cavils of feſh and blood, I oppoſe once for all THE WORD OF GOD and the truth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3307:4"/>therof, wherby I doubt not but to ſtop the mouth of proud fleſh, and to preſſe the ſame with the mace of Gods iudgements for evermore, except they imbrace and obey the truth.</p>
            <p>And therfore I do here in the preſence of God &amp; his Angels charge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whoſoever they be into whoſe ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds this preſent trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe ſhal come, that they preſume not to ſuffer the former cavils to haue paſſage out of their lippes, as being reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of any force, why the truth of God ſhould be beaten back, ſmothered and kept in, becauſe men do account the ſame to be mean, odious, offenſive, ſterne, proud, &amp;c. For why ſhould not all the world lay their hand upon their mouthes, when the GOD OF HEAVEN ſpeaketh, and labour to frame themſelves and their affections meet to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his truth, and to be obedient to the ſame? Shall proud men reiect it, becauſe it derogateth from their ruinous credite? Shal they ſeek to keep it under, becauſe they will not come under the line and direction of the ſame? Shall that be accounted odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, which is moſt amiable, moſt bewtifull, to be deſired above fine gold,<note place="margin">Job. 28.19.</note> yea of more valew then the <hi>Topaz of Aethiopia or the moſt pure wedge of the gold of Ophir,</hi> and that onely becauſe vaine men hate to be reformed by it? Shall that be accounted proud, offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, and haughty, wherat none poſſiblie can ſtumble but proud ſcribes and phariſees, or ignorant and worldly minded Diſciples, who wil not ſtick to ſay to the Lord himſelf, that his ſayings are hard and who can hear them? Nay let vaine men labour to haue the eare of the learned, that they may break in pieces their tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning away, to their ſhame &amp; confuſion of face, their hard intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the truth and thoſe that profeſſe the ſame, by revilings, ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, impriſonments &amp;c. to their everlaſting perdition, without the Lords great mercy in turning them unto him, which I ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly wiſh them.</p>
            <p>And as the whole truth oppugned in theſe dayes, is in the eyes men of the nature and qualitie before mentioned, ſo is this in particular, for the clearing wherof I am to deal at this preſent.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:3307:4"/>The point is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it is unlawfull for any of what eſtate, ſex, degree, &amp; condition ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they be, to communicate in any action of religion, as in hearing trueth taught, in receiving the Sacraments, praying, &amp;c. Within any of the publik meetings of the Land, as now they ſtand by Law:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therfore that this preſent Parliament &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſons of the firſt degree alleadged to prove the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wil be theſe, namely that the aſſertion is traiterous, ſeditious, ſchiſmatical: that it is Browniſme, that it is odious, offenſive &amp;c. that it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demneth the doings of the children of God, &amp; the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes of the moſt notable ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of Chriſt: accuſeth them all this while to have erred &amp; gone aſtray: that it croſſeth the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of reformed Churches; who are better perſwaded of the aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blies of the land: that excellent and famous men ſawe not this: that they were of an other mind &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But what is all this to the truth? is it any new thing to ſee the truth arraigned, indighted, condemned, and executed for trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and ſedition, though never convinced of the ſame? We con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider not whether kingdomes &amp; ſtates be ſo out of order as that the truth cannot come to light, but it wil be accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted traiterous among them, The onely thing that we eſpecially reſpect is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be truth or not, the which being found, hold it we muſt, defend it we muſt, whatſoever account mans corruption maketh therof. And therfore here is no more ſaid againſt it, but what in all ages hath bene falſly vttered againſt the truth. Falſey I ſay, becauſe no truth can be traiterous unto the ſtate of any Prince or Potentate. And as vnto this in particular, it ſhalbe found to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vndoubted ſtability with it, for the vpholding of her MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IESTIES crowne, authority, priviledges, preheminences with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all her Realmes and Dominions, and to be accompanied with the allowance of her Royall Lawes, if it might haue the particular benefit of them.</p>
            <p>Touching the crime of <hi>Browniſme, Schiſme,</hi> &amp;c. It is an vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3307:5"/>ſlaunder, for truth holdeth of no creature, it is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved onely from that head in whom all the treaſures of wiſedome and knowledge are hidden, that is from IESVS CHRIST: yet this I know to be the vſuall badge of the truth, to be called af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the names of men, to be accounted ſchiſmatical, that thereby the harts of the ſimple may be alienated from the ſame. And Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan in this latter age hath bene a mervelous cunning Rhetoricia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this way, there hath bene no truth brought to light, but he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h taken paines to paint it out for <hi>Zwinglianiſme Luther aniſme, Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, Browniſme, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Odious and offenſive it hath bene already graunted to be, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their eyes who refuſe to be guided by the line and rule of the Maiſter builder: wheras otherwiſe it is precious vnto them, that labour to ſquare themſelves and their actions according to the paterne of the holy ſanctuary and temple.</p>
            <p>And to pretend againſt the truth, that it condemneth the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of men, is nothing els but a manifeſt teſtimony that truth is truth: who muſt bear rule, and bring all into order: yea let all men in the world be liars, and let the Lord in this truth of his ordinances be iuſtified and prevaile.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 11.17. &amp; 12.9.11.</note> David is a godlie man, he is the ſweet ſinger of Iſrael, a man according to Gods own hart, wel eſteemed of, wel reputed: may he therfore do what he wil? may he continue in ſinne, and muſt not the light reproove him? Peter is the notable embaſsadour of Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.11.14.</note> a great inſtrument and furtherer of the truth: but may he therefore clayme liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie not to be withſtood to his face in his hypocriſie? If this could be once graunted, that the credit of men might cover their open breach of Gods lawe, and their continuance therin, it were but vaine to bring the truth to light. Nay let the credit of the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes of the congregation be hanged againſt the ſunne, rather then their place eſtimation and the good opinion which men haue received of them ſhould defend the whoring of the people with the daughters of Moab,<note place="margin">Num. 28.4.</note> eſpecially their ſpiritual whordome with the ordinances of Antichriſt, and their proud reiecting of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Touching reformed Churches, we are to walk by the line of the word, and not after the iudgements of men: When they have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3307:5"/>ſwered the reaſons ſet downe in this treatiſe, and have learned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in what ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the aſſemblies of the land do ſtand, we wil give ſome better doome vnto their opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. In the mean time we have a ſure word of the Prophets, wherevnto all thoſe are to give eare,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.19.</note> who purpoſe to folow the light of the true day ſtarr. If men ſpeak not according to this word, but wilfully runne from the light therof, to ſee what cloak they may have from Churches or men to cover their nakednes, we muſt needs tel them with the holy Prophet, that they do this,<note place="margin">Iſa. 8.20.</note> becauſe there is not a glimſe of light in them: And that they do not ſuffer themſelves to be tried by the light of the word, becauſe their works are in darknes. The caſe is marveilous ſtrange, that we having the written word of God at home, and the things accuſed by the ſame to be out of order, preſent before our eyes, ſhall runne from the word, and from common ſenſe, ſo farr alſo from home, to ask the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of men, in that caſe which on the one ſide they know not aright, and therfore cannot pronounce an equal ſentence therof, yea when their iudgements are gotten, there is no more had but the concluſions of men againſt the direct warrant of the word. The hierarchie hath ſo long time fought with this weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as it is a wonderfull caſe that thoſe who have dulled the edge therof by the buckler of the word, ar not aſhamed to take it vp themſelves. But what ſhift can there be ſo mean that Satan wil not vſe, for the covering of his ſhifting polluted marchandiſe? Yet is he and his vtterly beſides the mark if they think that we regard the perſons of men in this truth which we have in hand. Nay, if they were Angels from heaven, accurſed be they, if they go about in the leaſt point to ſeduce vs from the truth and word of Ieſus Chriſt our Maiſter.</p>
            <p>In whoſe behalf at this inſtant, I do here in his preſence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heaven and earth, arraigne and convince the whole pariſh-aſſemblies of this Land, and the members therof, as traytors and conſpiring with Antichriſt againſt his Maieſty, and conſequently as being ſuch at this preſent, as from whome every member of CHRIST is to ſeparate himſelf vnder paine of Gods everlaſting wrath.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:3307:6"/>Wherfore hearken ye ô heavens, and hear thou ô earth, &amp; let poſteritie bear witnes (ſeing this age ſtoppeth her eares) that I accuſe theſe pariſh-aſſemblies of being guilty of a greater conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy againſt the Maieſtie of Ieſus Chriſt, then that of Corah, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and Abiram was againſt Moſes: And therfore alſo of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in danger of the Lords indignation in a more fearful ſort the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were thoſe who abode with Corah and his company. The caſe with Corah, Dathan, and Abiram was thus.</p>
            <p>There were three eſpeciall prerogatives belonging vnto the ſonnes of Iſrael,<note place="margin">Gen. 49.3.4. 1 Chron. 5.</note> I. the kingdome. 2. the birthright. 3. the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly office of the Prieſthood. <hi>Reuben</hi> the firſt borne ſhould have bene excellent in ſome of theſe, as the Spirit of God recordeth, had he not defiled his fathers bed, but for this his ſinn he loſt his preferment. <hi>Symeon</hi> being the next, loſt the ſame in like manner for his ſlaughter of the <hi>Schecemites,</hi> in ſuch ſort as he was diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Iacob &amp; ſcattered in Iſrael, having never any proper tribe or inheritance after their owne name. <hi>Levi</hi> being a brother in miſcheif with him was alſo ſcattered: yet the Lord in mercy vouchſafed him the dignity of the Prieſthood,<note place="margin">1 Chron. 5.1.</note> as he did the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vnto Iuda, and the Birthright vnto Ioſeph, who had two tribes, and ſo a double portion amongeſt the children of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>Now at the comming out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> Moſes (by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of God I know) conveighed both the kingdome (that is the chief power of the civil authoritie) as alſo the prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, vnto his own fathers houſe. And in regard of the prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood he eſtabliſhed it for ever in the line of Aaron his brother by a covenant of ſalt. And to this purpoſe enacted that not onely the whol tribe of Levi, even <hi>Gerſhom</hi> the elder brother and his ſonnes ſhould be vnder the iuriſdiction and commandement of Aaron and his ſonnes, in the holy ſervice of the tabernacle, but alſo that none (Aaron and his ſonnes excepted) either of the Levites,<note place="margin">Num. 3.10: &amp; 4.10.</note> or of any other the tribes of Iſrael, ſhould intermeddle with the holy office of the prieſthood under paine of death.</p>
            <p>Herevpon certain famous men of the congregation, <hi>Corah</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:3307:6"/>of the houſe of Levi, <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> of the houſe of Reuben the firſt borne,<note place="margin">Num. 16.10. &amp; 17.5.8.</note> with other two hundred and fifty captaines of the aſſemblie, even all men of renowne, charged Moſes and Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of colluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; evil dealing with the Lords people, in that they had transferred the prieſthood vnto their fathers houſe without warrant: &amp; ſo the Lord was faine to decide the controverſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, not onely by his iudgements vpon the chief conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators and ſuch as abode in their tents, but alſo by the budding of Aarons rodde.</p>
            <p>Now touching the controverſie between Moſes and Corah, it was not whether the God of Iſrael was to be ſerved or not, for <hi>Corah</hi> and his company granted that as well as Moſes: It was not whether forreigne Idolatrie ſhould be brought into the houſe of Iſrael, for that would <hi>Corah</hi> and his company withſtand as wel as Moſes: breifly, it was not concerning any fundamentall point of religion (as men now vſe to ſpeak) but onely touching thoſe offices,<note place="margin">Num. 16.10.</note> and thoſe officers wherby the worſhip of God was to be performed: even touching the Prieſts office, as Moſes ſaith.</p>
            <p>In regard of the perſons, it may ſeem to be ſomthing tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, they were all of them members of the true viſible Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their conſpiracie: all famous men in the congregation:<note place="margin">1 Chon. 6.39.37.38.</note> And <hi>Corah</hi> in particular brought vp his children in the fear of God in ſuch meaſure as they wil have a famous name in the Church for evermore,<note place="margin">Num. 26.11.</note> as being thoſe who conſented not vnto their fathers ſinnes, and therfore alſo periſhed not with them, but were after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward imployed in the holy offices.</p>
            <p>Wel, the caſe of <hi>Corah</hi> being thus tollerable in the iudgement of fleſh and blood, yet was it vtterly vnlawful for any man, either to preach the truth, or to heare the truth taught within their tents. And therfore much more unlawful to preach the ſame, or to heare the ſame taught within any of the aſſemblies of England this day: Becauſe all theſe aſſemblies are not within the tents, that is vnder the iuriſdiction, and of the conſpiracie which <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> &amp; <hi>Abiram</hi> raiſed againſt <hi>Moſes:</hi> but within the tents, that is, under the power, and of the conſpiracie which the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3307:7"/>and officers of Antichriſt have raiſed againſt <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> the ſonne of God: And that it may be ſeen that I ſpeak the truth, I appeale to the conſciences of all men in this place, whether all the Pariſh-aſſemblies of <hi>England</hi> are not, yea and continue in ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto theſe offices of the Antichriſtian kingdome, namely, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Archbiſhop, a Lord biſhop, a Chancellor, an Archdeacon, a Commiſſary, an Off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ciall, and an other Preiſt at the leaſt, that is eyther a Parſon, a Vicar, or a Curate. Now touching the conſpiracy wherof theſe men are guiltie, I do agayn appeale vnto the conſciences of all men, whether it be not greater preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for Lord Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Chancellors, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſaries, Archdeacons, &amp;c. to ſay vnto <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> that he taketh too much vpon him, in a peaceable kingdome, to appoint by what offices and officers he ſhould be ſerved, then for Corah, Dathan, &amp; Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram to ſay, Moſes and Aaron you take too much vpon you.</p>
            <p>I know it muſt needs be granted to be greater: for ſhall they be accounted rebels that break Moſes his law, the violaters wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of died without mercy vnder two or three witneſſes: and will it not be adiudged much more heynous thus to rebel againſt the ſonne of God? The Spirit of God ſayth, yea: becauſe this man, to wit,<note place="margin">Heb. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> is worthy of more honour then Moſes. And he that breaketh his Law, (eſpecially) entreth into conſpiracie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, is a far greater traitor, then he that riſeth againſt the ordinances of Moſes.</p>
            <p>The concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then is evident, that the conſpiracy of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops and Biſhops of this land againſt <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> wherby they being forreigne Officers and ſtraungers from the houſe of God, by vertue of their Offices, do yet preſume to arrogate the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his houſe into their owne hands, &amp; to take vp weapons againſt him and his ſervants that would reſtore him into his own poſſeſsion, are greater Rebels, and guiltie of a greater ſin againſt the Maieſtie of God, then were <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> &amp; <hi>Abiram</hi> &amp; their company: And that thoſe who continue, and have eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call authoritie and iuriſdiction, are guilty of an high ſinne, and to expect a more fearful hand of God over them, then thoſe who
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3307:7"/>remayned in the tents of <hi>Corah Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be here obiected that theſe Romiſh Locuſts &amp; their guard do not ſay that Chriſt taketh too much vpon himſelf, in going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to plant what Offices he thinketh meet in his owne houſe, they mend not themſelves, for he that heareth you, heareth me, ſaith <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and he that deſpiſeth his word, reiecteth him: &amp; againe, <hi>Corah</hi> did not profeſſe himſelfe to riſe againſt the God of Iſrael, yet ſayth Moſes vnto him, <hi>Thou and all thy company are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together againſt the Lord, for what is Aaron that ye murmure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him?</hi> So ſay we vnto this Romiſh traine, ye and your abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors are gathered together this day againſt <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and have wreſted the Scepter out of his hand: as for vs that oppoſe our ſelves againſt you in our Maiſters quarrel, what are we that ye ſhould thus moleſt and perſecute vs?</p>
            <p>If any man ſhall plead ignorance for them, and ſay, that they ſee not what they do in theſe things: we anſwer, that the queſtion is not what they know, but what they doe. They have had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient time to learne now theſe 34 yeares and vpward, wherin they haue continued and increaſed their rebellion, and their practiſes againſt <hi>CHRIST JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> &amp; his Saints: Let them put on armour, and pitch a feild againſt her MAIESTIE, moleſt and perſequute her ſubiects, deſpiſe her proclamations, and impriſon to the death her faithfulleſt ſervants: and ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pleading ignorance wil cover their attempts. Much leſſe wil it ſerve their turne in this caſe: And if they are ignorant, then ſpeak they evil of, and perſequute that which they know not, and ſo are in a fearful caſe. But <hi>Corah</hi> and his company living in a time of ſmaller light, having alſo ſome more reaſons to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their attempts (as before hath, and agayn ſhalbe briefly tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched) might plead ignorance better then our Prelacy and Preiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood may do.</p>
            <p>Wherfore eyther it muſt be ſayd that men may conſpire againſt IESVS CHRIST without controlment, wheras this could not be done vnder and againſt Moſes, without the danger of a fore recompenſe of Gods wrath, Or els it muſt be graunted that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3307:8"/>the conſpiracie of our Prelates muſt be farre greater then that of <hi>Corah Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> was, which can in no wiſe be denied, both becauſe it aymeth at the ſame point, that <hi>Corahs</hi> did, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the outward offices of the houſe of God (to ſpeak nothing here of the will-worſhip and falſe adminiſtrations, wherein theſe Romiſh Offices are imployed in the aſſemblies of this Land) and alſo in as much as it is againſt <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> the Sonne, wheras the gainſaying of <hi>Corah</hi> withſtood but the ordinances appointed by Moſes the ſervant.</p>
            <p>And therfore alſo it followeth, that ſeing the aſſemblies of this Land cannot be drawen to leave the tents of theſe wicked men, but continue in the wilful and obſtinate defence of this their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it followeth (I ſay) that they are alſo guilty of a greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie, then thoſe were that abode in the tents of <hi>Corah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What theſe pariſh aſſemblies wil be able to ſay for themſelves I know not: for it is out of controverſie true, that all of them are at the commaundement &amp; under the iuriſdiction of theſe Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Captaynes. They receive no Miniſterie, but what they allow, what they make, what hath authoritie from them: They receive no worſhip, &amp; manner of ſerving the true God but what theſe Romiſh Apollyons are content ſhalbe over them. Nay, they are wholly their ſubiects, and at their call and commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in every thing that apperteyneth vnto the outward worſhip of the Lord. When this gainſaying generation graunteth the Pariſh a preaching Preiſt, they have a Preacher: when they deny the ſame, they muſt be content with reading. Not to be long in a knowen caſe, what can there be done in theſe aſſemblies, which the Prelates are not content to tollerate and allow? Nay what power hath the Pariſh or their Preiſt, to eſtabliſh any thing there, but what they derive from their Ordinary?</p>
            <p>And as to the moſt Pariſhes in this Land, &amp; Preiſts that ſerve in them, they profeſſedly mainteyn this conſpiracie. Some few preaching Preiſts or Deacons, and ſome ſmall number of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, I graunt to be here and there which pretend a deſire to have this conſpiracie diſſolved, but theſe are nothing to the generall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3307:8"/>ſtate of the Land. And theſe in the mean time are alſo themſelves the cheif vpholders of this conſpiracie, holding it lawful (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the expreſſe inhibition of the word) for themſelves and all others to continue within theſe tents, in ſuch ſort as they are become the cheifeſt mainteyners of this Rebellion, &amp; the egereſt purſuers of thoſe that leave the ſame. For if any man ſhal accuſe eyther them, or theſe famous Captaynes the Archbiſhops, and Lordbiſhops, Preiſts, Archdeacons <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be an Antichriſtian band riſen vp againſt <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp; therfore ſuch as from whoſe aſſemblies everie ſervant of Chriſt is to ſever himſelf: theſe prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and other people preſently band themſelves gainſt him for a Schiſmatick, and a Browniſt. And they wil leave no weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnhandeled, no meanes vnaſſayed, eyther of abuſing the word, or of fair ſpeaking, ſlandering reviling, <hi>&amp;c</hi> vntil (if poſsibly by that furniture they may)they hav turned him into thoſe tents agayn, the which they can prove to be <hi>Schems,</hi> wherevnto the Lord hath promiſed to perſwade <hi>Japheth</hi> to enter, and not <hi>Corahs</hi> or Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts, from the which and out of the which he calleth his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by a loud voice, ſaying,<note place="margin">Num. 16.26. 2 Cor. 6.16.17.</note> 
               <hi>Depart now from the tentes of theſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, and touch nothing that is theirs, leaſt you periſh in all their ſinnes.</hi> And, <hi>Come out from among them, ſeparate your ſelves, and touch no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean thing, and I wil receive you ſayth the Lord.</hi> For what fellowſhip hath righteouſnes with vnrighteouſnes? what communion hath light with darknes? what concord hath Chriſt with Belial? Or what part hath the beleever with the infidel? So that if we conſider theſe people, although they are nothing to the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of the Land, behold a company of conſpirators as wel as the reſt, even thoſe who are as much ſubiect vnto the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolment, &amp; no leſſe under the iuriſdiction of Lord Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Archdeacons, Chancellors, then any other of the land: and as to their meetings, they are the ſame with all the reſt of the ignorant ſort, who are members as wel as they.</p>
            <p>And here, we are not to regard whether men be deſirous to be out of the tents of <hi>Corah,</hi> becauſe they had rather ioyn with <hi>Moſes,</hi> or fear the Lord wrath that is like to inſue vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wicked habitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:3307:9"/>but whether they continue there or not. If they continue there, then may we ſay vnto them, that they ſhal periſh in all their ſinns. They muſt needs touch their vncleanneſſe, they muſt have fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, nay ſtoup and yeeld reverence and obeiſance vnto the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous ordinances of Antichriſt, which are laid and impoſed on them in ſteed of the ordinances of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> They appear at their Courts, pay and bring their fees, to kindle and mainteyn that fire vpon Baals altar, which otherwiſe would be eaſily quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. They ioyne in prayer, hearing, ſacraments, and every o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther action, wherby the conſpirators pollute the religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo that they are not ſeparated from, they are the ſame with, they come not out from among theſe Rebels. They confeſsing them ſelves to be light, have communion and fellowſhip with theſe moſt uncleane ordinances of the kingdome of darknes, which they ſhould withſtand, gainſay, reprove, and avoid, though with the peril of their lives. They participate, they communicate with the Ordinances of the vnbeleeving Antichriſtian race: nay with the Ordinances of Divels, though they confeſſe themſelves to be beleevers: The Ordinances of Divels (I ſay) for all the inventions of the kingdome of Antichriſt, all the members and officers of that child of perdition, as Archbiſhops, Lord biſhops, Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, Commiſſaries, Archdeacons, Preiſts, Officials, and their iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictions, were invented by the mighty power of Satan, as the Apoſtle teacheth vs. They ſay they are Chriſtes, and yet ioyne themſelves with the ordinances of Belial, are ſubiect vnto him, &amp; at his commandement in his ſayd ordinances. And therfore let them ſay what they wil, theſe alſo, who would be otherwiſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted, ioyne light and darknes together, righteouſnes &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſnes, Chriſt and Belial, and conſequently are vnited in the ſame band of Rebellion, and conſpiracy againſt Chriſt Ieſus, with theſe forenamed leaders. Whervpon it followeth that the whol aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blies of the land &amp; every member of them, do not onely continue within theſe Antichriſtian tabernacles that are pitched vp againſt Ieſus Chriſt, that is, under the iuriſdiction and at the commandement, direction, and government of thoſe Maiſterful
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3307:9"/>Rebels and conſpirators, the Lord Archbiſhops, and Biſhops, Prieſts, Chancellors of the Land, but alſo are found to cary ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour againſt Ieſus Chriſt and his members vnder the banner of theſe foreſayd Rebels.</p>
            <p>Yet the queſtion here is not ſo much whether a Levite or any other of the children of Iſrael agreing with <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> in conſent and action, might remaine within their tents, as, whether any, diſliking the conſpiracie, might yet abide in that rebellious campe, vpon ſome other reſpect or purpoſe: it is anſwered, no: ſeing the Lord abſolutely commaundeth all to depart. So that it would not ſerve a Levite to ſay, I may here preach the truth: <hi>Corah</hi> and his company are brethren, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the true Religion: they erre in no fundamental point: the matter of their overſight is rather in manners, then in doctrine: Though it were in doctrine, yet is it onely touching the outward offices of the houſe of God: <hi>Corah</hi> thinketh it much that he and his ſhould be made perpetual ſervants, vnto Aaron &amp; his ſonns: There are many famous men of his iudgement, even two hundred and fifty Captaynes of the Congregation: The moſt of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are of the ſame mind, and alas ſhould theſe want teaching? They have conceived ſuch a deep impreſsion of hatred againſt Moſes and Aaron, that as yet they wil not be gotten to come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their tents though they ſhould dy for it: The whol aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the Lords people both one &amp; other think much that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſhould eſtabliſh both the Scepter and the Preiſtood in his own fathers houſe:<note place="margin">Num. 16.13.14.</note> Eſpecially <hi>Dathan</hi> &amp; <hi>Abiram</hi> the ſonnes of <hi>Reu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben</hi> the firſt borne cannot brook this: All of them charge Moſes very heavily of breach of promiſe, of ſeducing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by faire words to come out of Egypt, that he might be made a Lord and ruler over them: He promiſed them inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of fields &amp; vineyards, &amp; therby brought them out for a land that floweth with milke and hony, and yet behold they are all this while in a barren and fearful wilderneſſe, where they can get neither bread to eat, nor yet water to drink for themſelves and their cattel: Farre be it that we ſhould iudge all theſe to be reprobates that are of this
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3307:10"/>mind. Many of them are known to be good ſoules and to carrie a good heart to the glorie of God. The time was when Moſes himſelfe was not of that mind, that he would have none to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice but Aaron and his ſonnes: Nay we would have ben glad all of vs when we were in Egypt, to have had but halfe the libertie &amp; quietnes to ſerve our God, that we may have within the tents of <hi>Corah:</hi> we may teach the whole ſubſtance of the truth there, yea &amp; that alſo which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerneth the outward Offices, ſo that we do it wiſelie &amp; diſcreetly. It is an hard matter therfore for vs to leave our places here, and the good which we may do vnto Gods glory by inſtructing the people. For alas ſhould theſe periſh for want of inſtructers? Or ſhall they be taught by none but ſuch as <hi>Corah</hi> would thruſt over them, if we give place? How then ſhal the poor people be inſtructed? If we ſhall continue a while among them, we doubt not but in ſhort ſpace to draw al of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agayn to Moſes and Aaron, &amp; to reſtore the true callings &amp; functions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. Here may a ſubſtance of a calling be had, for we are <hi>Levites,</hi> the people are the ſonnes of <hi>Iaakob,</hi> they are no Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters. When their heat wherein they are now carried againſt Moſes and Aaron is ſomewhat better allaied, we doubt not but to accompliſh this among them, though as yet it were folly to vrge any ſuch matter: we have other points inough wherein to teach the people.</p>
            <p>Theſe I ſay, and ſuch like purpoſes would not ſtand a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite in any ſtead to colour his abode amonge theſe conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators, nay he might be aſſured that Gods iudgements would ſeaze vpon him in a moment, if he abide the comming thereof. And yet the Preiſts or Preachers of our time, can alleadge no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſons why they will continue to teach vnder this falſe hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie, and at the appointment, and direction thereof, then the former which I have ſet downe. And if they could not be of force to colour the abiding within the tentes of Corah, much leſſe ſhal they beare out the continuance within the tents of theſe conſpirators which have riſen vp againſt <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and wil not permit him to reigne in his Ordinances. For the Proclamation is as cleere againſt the continuance within and vnder the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3307:10"/>Dominions, as it was againſt the abode within <hi>Corahs</hi> tents. And therfore except men think that they may preſume to attempt that againſt Ieſus Chriſt which they durſt not vndertake againſt Moſes, their preſumption is highly prodigious, who dare vnder the ſhadow of the forenamed figge leaves exerciſe a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie (as they account it) vnder the iuriſdiction, and by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of the forenamed Antichriſtian generation, over theſe poor, miſerable, ſeduced captives, which they keep within their conſpiring hoaſt.</p>
            <p>They wil ſay, that the Prelates ar brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they hold the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Religion, that they have many of their iudgement that are none of the worſt men, that many of them teach the truth in the greateſt and weightieſt points of religion. Why? ſo might be ſayd of <hi>Corah.</hi> They wil ſay, they may teach the foundations &amp; grounds of religion vnder them, even preach <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> truely. How true they ſay this, ſhalbe afterward touched: but ſo they might within the tents of <hi>Corah.</hi> Breifly they can alleage nothing for themſelves this way, but what hath bene already ſet down, in the behalf of <hi>Corahs</hi> gainſaying.</p>
            <p>Againe, touching the continuance of the miſerable people of the Land within theſe Antichriſtian aſſemblies, although their caſe be more to be pitied, then their Phariſaicall leaders: yet can they ſay nothing for themſelves alſo, but what an Iſraelite of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rahs</hi> conſpiracie might alleadge. The word they have, the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they have, corruptly they wil grant: ſo might it be ſaid of <hi>Corahs</hi> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. But we demand of them, whether they haue the ſame within theſe aſſemblies who with Archbiſhops and Biſhops haue conſpired to keepe out <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> in his Ordinances? or els in thoſe meetings where the ſonne of God doth reigne in his owne order, It is a plaine caſe, that they haue theſe things in the gayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying aſſemblies. For as before I have ſaid and as all the world doth know, all the aſſemblies of this Land do profeſſedly conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue members of this outragious conſpiracie againſt the ſonne of God. And as for the Preachers themſelves, there are none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but they bear office, within this rebellious band, &amp; make vp the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpirators the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves. What ſhould I ſay, bear office? Nay they are but ſervants &amp; vaſſals amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g theſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpiring Rebels.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3307:11"/>And whatſoever they do in theſe aſſemblies, it is no more then what thoſe forenamed <hi>Abaddons</hi> wil give them leave. For it is wel knowne that there is not a preaching Preiſt or Deacon in the land, but he is an vnderling to an Archbiſhop, a Lordbiſhop, a Chancellor, a Commiſſarie, an Archdeacon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that he can preach no otherwiſe, inſtruct his Pariſhioners no otherwiſe, take no other order with them, then thoſe his forenamed Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters wil give him leave. They may every one of them ſend for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Pariſh-preacher in the land, cite him, control him, cenſure him, and he dares not but obey vnder payne of being dumbe &amp; ſpeechleſſe, if they lyſt to charge him vnder ſuch a penalty. And is he not a ſervant then?</p>
            <p>Let it not be here obiected, that there are ſome Abbey pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, Celles, Nunneries, Frieries &amp;c where a Preacher may be exempted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the iuriſdiction of his Ordinary, by vertue of ſome old Romiſh priviledge: for theſe are nothing to the whole caſe of the land. And there is none of theſe but the Arch-prelates know wel inough how to bring them vnder the ſubiection, and at the commaundement of the meaneſt Commiſſary and Archdeacon in the Land. Wherby their Romiſh priviledge can ſtand them in no ſtead. And are they not ſervants then? Nay all the forenamed Officers have more to do within any Pariſh in the land, for cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring, ſuſpending, excommunicating, then the Pariſh preacher hath: for he is an vnderling vnto them all, yea a Churchwarden hath more to do in many things with his Pariſhioners, then he hath. And is he not a ſervant then? Nay hath he not his office, his flock, and the work of his Miniſtery according to the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on manner and cuſtome of theſe Tents, and no otherwiſe then theſe tents wil bear the ſame? It cannot be denied. Doth he not then bear Office within this conſpiring band, and make vp the number of theſe Rebels? Yea this is the onely vſe that is made of the beſt teaching in the land at this day, that it keepeth the poore people within theſe tabernacles of the Romane hierarchie, who otherwiſe (were it not for theſe Teachers) would vtterly reiect this Antichriſtian yoke. And therfore a ſhame it is to ſpeak of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3307:11"/>teaching of theſe times, ſeing it is apparanr to be one of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt baites wherby the poor deluded people of the land that have any hart vnto religion, are kept within the forenamed Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hoaſt. And therefore the whol land, and all the aſſemblies therof are over iuſtly charged of being guiltie of a greater rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the Maieſtie of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> then thoſe fearfull Rebels were, which abode within the tents of <hi>Corah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be here demanded what the people ſhould do, we ſay that they ſhould follow the counſell of the holy Ghoſt, who ſayth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, <hi>Depart from the Tents of theſe wicked men,</hi> And, <hi>Come out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among them my people, and touch none vnclean thing, and I wil receiv you.</hi> And againe, <hi>Goe out of her my people, that yee be not partak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs of her ſinnes, and that yee receive not of her plagues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here I would know what it is that keepeth them here: If they ſay, the word and ſacraments, they are anſwered againe, that they traffique in other merchandiſe of Antichriſts meere inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on beſides theſe. For they go unto <hi>Corahs</hi> owne Courts, and are at <hi>Abaddons</hi> commaundement, in the things which he himſelf hath invented, as well as in thoſe points wherin he turneth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into an Angel of light, and becommeth like the Miniſter of righteouſnes. And if it be for the Word and Sacraments onely, that they remaine, then I truſt they wil hold it vnlawful for them ſelves, or for any other to communicate in the merchandiſe which is meerly whooriſh and Antichriſtian, as reſorting to the Prelates Courts to be cenſured by them, comunicating with them <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is the Prieſt onely or the Deacon that admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtreth the word and the Sacraments. If they continue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe tents onely for the love that they have vnto theſe things, then I truſt they will have nothing to do with the Lord Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop, the Lordbiſhop, the Commiſſarie, Chancellor, Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, Official <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and their traffique they bring with them. Let them withdraw themſelves from under their iuriſdiction, &amp; they ſhall ſee how long they can have quietnes within theſe tents.</p>
            <p>But if they think (as it is the practiſe of all) that they may alſo be at the commaundement of theſe forenamed <hi>Corahs, Dathans</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:3307:12"/>and <hi>Abirams,</hi> then have they nothing to cover their wicked hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, but they muſt be inforced to confeſſe that they are not perſwaded in their conſciences, but that they may be members of thoſe aſſemblies which conſpire againſt <hi>Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they durſt not preſume to continue within the tents of thoſe that aſſembled themſelves againſt Moſes the ſervant. And ſo they reſt in undoubted expectation of a more fearefull judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, then fel vpon thoſe that would not depart from the Tents of <hi>Corah Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what they ſpeak of the word &amp; ſacraments, is before an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, in as much as they of <hi>Corahs</hi> conſpiracie might as well hav ſtaied within their tents for theſe reſpects, as they may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the aſſemblies of England. And the point is not what they may have in theſe aſſemblies, but whether they may ſtay there or not, whatſoever is there to be found? We ſay, they ought not to ſtay. They ſeeme not to deny it, in that they bring no reaſon out of the word to prove the lawfulnes of their abode there, but onely reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which they may have there. Wheras firſt they ſhould prove, that they may ſtay in a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpiring &amp; peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly, before they tell vs what it is that they may have in the ſame. They are ſimply inſtructed in the truth which is according to godlines, that have not as yet learned that the whoriſh ſynagogues are dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with many of the Iewels that belong to the true ſpouſe.</p>
            <p>But touching the word and Sacraments, which they ſeem to poſſeſſe there, I ſay that within the tents of <hi>Corah,</hi> though the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites do teach the truth and adminiſter circumciſion, yet is not this that truth or that circumciſion which hath the promiſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed vnto them, and therefore not that truth or thoſe ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments wherewith any of the children of God may participate as long as they are adminiſtred in that gainſaying Aſſemblie. Let thoſe truthes which they teach and thoſe ſacraments which they adminiſter be brought out of theſe wicked tents, and brought before the Lords Tabernacle as he commandeth: and then are they to be received, to be embraced, and accounted more preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then much fine gold, and ſweeter then the hony, or the hony
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3307:12"/>combe: Otherwiſe the Saints of God are not to taſt of them. Not that they ſhould reiect the truth at any tyme, but that they may not be deceived by an abuſed truth and an abuſed ordinance to pollute the holy things of God, and to violate the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Ieſus Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The like is to be ſaid of the truth taught, and the Sacraments adminiſtred in the aſſemblies of this Land: they are abuſed truthes, abuſed Sacraments, even ſuch truthes, and ſuch Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as wherby Satan would draw vs to be of the conſpiracie which is raiſed vp &amp; mainteyned here againſt Ieſus Chriſt. They are ſuch truthes and ſuch Sacraments, as are within the tents, that is, vnder the iuriſdiction of the kingdome of Antichriſt, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred onely vnto ſuch, as will receive the marks and badge of that kingdome, and vnto none other. For he that will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe himſelf even by his deedes to be a member of that aſſemblie wherin an Archbiſhop is an Officer, a Lord Biſhop is an Officer, a Chancellor is an officer, an Archdeacon is an Officer, a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is an Officer, a Preiſt is an Officer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he cannot receive them. And theſe abuſed truthes &amp; Sacraments are by the vnſpeakable ſubtiltie of Sathan reteyned in theſe ſynagogues, to the end that they may be made a bait to draw men, &amp; a grin to enſnare them to be ſubiect vnto Antichriſt in theſe his Ordinances before named.</p>
            <p>And therfore whereas men and women do pretend that they have the word and Sacraments here, it is but the net of deluſion which they weave to catch their owne ſoules and to keep them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſubiect vnto Satan. For it is not a bare truth, and a bare Sacrament that we are to ſeek after, but a truth, and a ſacrament that hath the warrant of the word with it. But as the outward man liveth not by bread, but by the word and promiſe of God that ſanctifieth bread vnto his vſe, So doth not the inward man of the ſoule live onely by the truth made knowen, or by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments adminiſtred, but much more by the word and promiſe of GOD, which make theſe effectuall when they are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred according to the ordinances of GOD.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3307:13"/>Theeves and robbers are fed we know to their ſacietie with the bread of violence and robberie, but they have no warrant of the word to eat any ſuch bread. So I know that the truth of God may be taught, and the Sacraments adminiſtred (I meane the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments which he appointed and none other,) among thoſe which are fallen away from him, which have conſpired againſt him. And the people of theſe aſſemblies may eſteem of them, &amp; think themſelves highly favoured, that they have them, and yet in the mean time have they no warrant that any ſuch truthes or Sacraments wilbe ſanctified vnto them, and ſo no warrant to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them.</p>
            <p>And therfore when we ſpeak of the word and ſacraments, we muſt firſt of all lay downe the promiſes of God and the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God, wherby we may aſſure our owne ſoules that this word and theſe ſacraments, are ſanctified vnto vs. Be it then that the word and ſacraments may be had in the aſſemblies of this land, yet is not that the point that we call in queſtion, but whether this word, and theſe ſacraments may be had here accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ordinances of God or not: otherwiſe we muſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them, we muſt refuſe them, not that we are at any time to reiect and refuſe the holy things of God, but that we are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect the abuſe of them, &amp; to take heed that in receiving of them, we be not drawen to break Gods ordinances. For when we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſeſſe the word and the ſacraments without ſinne, we muſt not do evil, that is, break the Lawe of our God, that good may come vnto vs thereof. The word is taught in the tents of <hi>Corah,</hi> circumciſion is adminiſtred there, it is not to be heard, not to be received, and why? becauſe they who adminiſter the ſame are a company of conſpirators againſt the God of Iſrael, at the leaſt they are in thoſe tents wherof the Lord hath ſayd, <hi>Come not neare the tents of theſe wicked men, and touch nothing of theirs, least yee be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers in all their ſinnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The caſe is the ſame with the aſſemblies of this land: the truth is taught ther, the ſacraments ar adminiſtred, or rather profaned, we wil in no wiſe communicate with them, becauſe theſe things
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3307:13"/>are done within the Tents not of <hi>Corah,</hi> but of the Officers &amp; members of the kingdome of Antichriſt, which ſay that <hi>Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> taketh too much vpon him if he will go about to appoint by what Offices his owne houſe and Church ſhould be ruled. They are under their iuriſdictions and their Offices of whome the Lord hath ſaid vnto vs, <hi>Come out from among them and touch no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean thing,</hi> for what communion hath the light of my word with the Tents of mine enemies, the puritie of my Sacraments, with thoſe polluted caves and dennes. So that from theſe things this Argument doth ariſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is at the leaſt as vnlawful, if not much more for any to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate in the word and ſacraments, or in any other action of religion, within the tents of the Kingdome of Antichriſt, as within the tents of Corah Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than and Abiram.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But to communicate in any of the Pariſh-aſſemblies of England is to communicate within the tents, that is, under the iuriſdiction of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Antichrist.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therfore as vnlawful, or rather much more to communicate in the actions of Religion, within theſe aſſemblies then it was within the tents of Corah, Dathan and Abiram.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What wil be here called into queſtion, I know not: if the firſt men think the tents of <hi>Corah</hi> were to be approched vnto, the caſe would be ſhameful, and the ignorance not to be heard, ſeing the Lord hath plainly inhibited the ſame, as hath bene ſet down. And if this were once graunted, then hath the Lord appointed his Ordinances, and his Miniſtery in vaine, and without cauſe, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men may of their owne heads appoint what Miniſterie they think meet, and continue vnder the ſame. Neither let it be here ſaid that the conſpiracy of <hi>Corah</hi> prevailed not, or that there were not many that agreed therevnto. For firſt as touching the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r point, the whole congregation were ſo affected towards theſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious rebels, that the next day after the Lord had exerciſed his fearful iudgements vpon them, the whole congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (I ſay) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed Moſes &amp; Aaron that they had ſlaine the Lords people, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Corah</hi> and his company, and fourteen thouſand of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3307:14"/>were conſumed for this their murmuring, which ſheweth what harts they bare vnto <hi>Corah,</hi> &amp; how likely he was to prevail with the whole rebellious hoaſt, had not the Lord by his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from heaven ſtaied the iniquitie. His conſpiracie continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not I graunt, and yet a greater, that is the conſpiracie of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt againſt Chriſt Ieſus hath continued now for many yeares. And the Lord hath ſet <hi>Corahs</hi> overthrowe for a ſigne vnto the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (eſpecially vnto the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpirators that ar riſen vp againſt Chriſt Ieſus,) that their ruine and fal ſhalbe in a moment, when they little exſpect the ſame. It is not to be doubted but it would have prevailed and continued (ſuch was the working of Satan in the harts of that murmuring hoaſt) had not the Lord ſtayed it by the preſent ſtreame of his fierie indignation.</p>
            <p>Neither is the conſpiracie of Antichriſt and his members to be thought more tollerable then that of Corahs, becauſe the Lord pleadeth not againſt the ſame with his viſible iudgements from heaven, as he did againſt the other, but wee are rather to learne, that what the Lord effected vnder the Law by his viſible iudgements, or other outward meanes being the rudiments of the world, as the Apoſtle calleth the things of this nature, the verie ſame doth the Lord accompliſh vnder the Goſpell againſt the ſonne of Perdition and his body by the ſpirit of his mouth, that is,<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.8.</note> by his mighty word and the operation thereof. And therfore although he overthrew and diſſolved that moſt fearfull conſpiracie of <hi>Corah Dathan</hi> &amp; <hi>Abiram</hi> by the arme of his dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full iudgements in a moment, yet farre be it that we ſhould think the conſpiracie of the members of Antichriſt againſt the right heire of the houſe of David, to be leſſe diſpleaſing in the ſight of God , becauſe in ſome meaſure he doth and of a long time hath with held the hand of his outward iudgements from the ſame, as having determined vtterlie to conſume and aboliſh that Apoſtaticall body, by no other ſpeciall meanes then by the brightnes of his appearing and comming in the Miniſterie of his Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:3307:14"/>And therefore the Propoſition abideth firme and ſure, that if it was vnlawful for any to communicate in the Actions of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion within the tents of Corah, it is much more vnlawfull for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to do ſo within and vnder the tents of Antichriſt, the great and high enemy of Ieſus Chriſt. For may we not have any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with them and their Tabernacles who ſay, <hi>Moſes and Aaron, you take too much vpon you:</hi> &amp; may we have fellowſhip with that campe who hath pitched a field againſt Ieſus Chriſt? and beare both Prince and people in hand that he taketh too much vpon him, in appointing who ſhall approch to miniſter in his preſence vnder the civil authoritie of a Chriſtian Prince? Could not the children of God have any ſanctified uſe of the Tents of <hi>Corah:</hi> and may they have the ſame of the tabernacles of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt which are invented and ordeyned to the overthrow of the prerogative of Ieſus, who is God over all bleſſed for evermore? This were nothing but to account Moſes to be the Lord, that is, to be eſteemed, reverenced, and had in eſtimation; and to rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon Chriſt Ieſus execrable, that is, baſe, contemptible, and mean, ſuch as whoſe lawes and ordinances may be violated, caſt of, &amp; troden vnder foot with leſſe perill then Moſes his might, which no man ſpeaking by the Spirit of God can hold and avouch.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As to the Aſſumption,</hi> That the Pariſh aſſemblies of England are under the iuriſdiction of the kingdome of Antichriſt: For the proof we are to ſet downe theſe groundes: Firſt that this manner of regiment by Archbiſhops, Lordbiſhops, Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, Archdeacons, Commiſſaries, is not any civill conſtitution, but an eccleſiaſticall, as all men know. For their Courts are ſpirituall Courts, and they ſpirituall Lords, and ſpirituall Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, deriving their offices in deed from that Spirit that ruleth in the aire. Next, being eccleſiaſticall, they belong either vnto the true Church of Chriſt, or to ſome malignant ſynagogue: but not to the true Church of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> for we know that the LORD when he furniſhed his body with all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers meet for the ſame, and beſtowed all the Offices thereon,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3307:15"/>wherewith it was at any time to be indued unto his ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, appointed no ſuch offices therin as theſe Locuſts are. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, they are a meer ſuperfluous and curſed addition vnto the Teſtament of Ieſus Chriſt, as all men that ever read the old and new Teſtament do know. For there are no ſuch Officers, or ſuch offices mentioned therin. And therfore they are the Tares which Satan the enemy of Ieſus Chriſt ſowed &amp; brought foorth, even the plantes which the Lord God hath not planted, &amp; ſo muſt be and ſhalbe rooted out of his vineyard: Yea they are no other the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Locuſts that came out of the bottomleſſe pit upon the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereof by that darkened ſtarre,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.3.</note> unto whom the key of the ſame pit was committed. Thirdly, belonging vnto the mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnant Church, they apperteyn either vnto the heatheniſh Pagan religion, or vnto the aſſemblie of Antichriſt that great Traitor &amp; enemie of Ieſus Chriſt: But not vnto the heathen religion, for there are no ſuch Offices, Officers, and forme of regiment to be found among them.</p>
            <p>Wherfore they do belong vnto no other body eccleſiaſticall or civill, but onely vnto that apoſtaticall kingdome which aroſe vp, and ſtil continueth vnder the name of Chriſt Ieſus, that is, the kingdome of Antichriſt. We are able to ſhew them their origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall with our finger, and alſo all the world will beare vs witnes that the Pope left them here to keep poſſeſſion for him, when at the beginning of her Maieſties reign he was throwen out with the reſt of his guard, the Cardinalls, Abbots, Priors, Monks, Friers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Further all ſocieties both eccleſiaſticall and civil can be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect without theſe Offices, and this forme of Regiment, ſave one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that right and well ordered ſocietie of the man of ſinne and his members. For the Church of Chriſt may be perfect and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute without theſe Egyptian graſhoppers: the civil Magiſtracie may be perfect without them: ſo may the heathen idolatrie too: But as for the hoaſt of the Romane Antichriſt, it ſhalbe altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnperfect, maimed and wanting the cheif members thereof, if it want Lord Archbiſhops and Biſhops, Deanes, Archdeacons, Chancellors, Commiſſaries, Officialls, to ſpeak nothing in this
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3307:15"/>place of Preiſtes &amp; Deacons, &amp; ſo of Chapleines, Parſons, Vicars, Curates, Canons, Prebendes, Singing men, Queriſters, Virgiers, which are conſpicuous markes whereby the beaſt is knowen, the name and number of his name made up and accompliſhed.</p>
            <p>Wherfore the concluſion is evident, that to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate in any action of religion within any of the Pariſh aſſemblies of this land is to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate &amp; be a member within the Tents, that is, under the iuriſdiction, power, and authoritie of the kingdome of that Romane Antichriſt the direct enimie of Ieſus Chriſt, and ſo to be in a more fearefull caſe, and in greater danger of the Lords wrath, then thoſe who remained within the Tentes of Corah, Dathan, and Abiram.</p>
            <p>Now to come to your Honours of this high Court of Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, I take heaven &amp; earth to witnes againſt you this day, that I have here on the behalf of my maiſter the Lord Ieſus Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menced a true action againſt the Pariſh-aſſemblies of this Land, even ſuch as you cannot deny to be true. For yee cannot denie the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of the Land to be ſubject unto the forenamed officers, and forme of Regiment, which being eccleſiaſticall, and not civill, as I have declared, the verie light of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſenſe and experience doth ſhewe unto you apperteine &amp; belong not unto the Church of Chriſt, nor unto any heathen Idolatrie, but onely unto the kingdome of Babell, that band of graven Images and ſea of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie. And would you have us to continue in Babell, ſeing our God calleth us out of the ſame by a mightie voice? telling us that he maketh no other account of any that continue within theſe Territorie, but as of thoſe that are become poiſoned Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons, unclean and polluted noiſome foules, and ſuch as haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion and fellowſhip with Divels: Threatning utter ruine unto us and our ſoules for evermore, if we ſhall any longer abide within theſe wicked bandes. Nay wil you of this Parliament ſuffer this curſed Iericho to ſtand any longer? will you ſuffer theſe te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to be pitched? this hoſt of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpirators to be maintained any longer within this Iland, againſt Ieſus Chriſt and his Saintes? Nay will you your ſelves continue any longer within this rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous campe, and not rather ſet theſe Midianitiſh Tentes on fire,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3307:16"/>&amp; throwe your ſelves downe &amp; theſe Rebellious Capteines alſo before the feet of IESVS CHRIST the true Captayn of the Lords hoaſt?</p>
            <p>For (my Lords, and you the reſt of this honourable aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie,) I am ſo far from doubting whether I &amp; my brethren have done amiſſe in leaving theſe Pariſhes of the Land, that I dare ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt your Honours and all others for conſpiring againſt the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the ſonne of God, and ſo againſt your owne ſalvation, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever you be that will preſume any longer to continue mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of theſe diſordered rebellious ſynagogues: And therfore do here, for the diſcharge of my duetie towards the Lord, &amp; you whom he hath placed in authoritie over me, require you to be ſo farre from following the humour of Adoni-bezek and the reſt of his proud confederates in making war againſt vs the poor Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beonites (who daring no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d out againſt the living God, have thrown our ſelves down at his feet that our ſoules might live) as you wil alſo take the ſame courſe with vs. For queſtionleſſe you ſhall find it true,<note place="margin">Act. 3.22. Deut. 18.19. with Eſa. 60.12.</note> that that Nation and that Perſon which will not heare and be obedient vnto this Prophet, and this King which the Lord hath raiſed vp to ſit vpon the throne of David, and to rule the ſame, ſhall be cut of from among his people. And touching the kingdome and the government, which his father hath given unto him, it cannot be transferred vnto another peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but it will break and deſtroy all the kingdomes that ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it,<note place="margin">Dan. 2.44.</note> and it ſhall ſtand for evermore.</p>
            <p>Wherfore (my Lords) if you purpoſe to ſet vp a kingdome for him, I do here in his name charge you to be ſo far from enacting any thing againſt vs in this preſent Parliament, who now oppoſe our ſelves vnto the forenamed Rebels, as you wil decree in his behalf at the leaſt as much as <hi>Nebuchad-netſer</hi> &amp; <hi>Darius</hi> being hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Princes did eſtabliſh:<note place="margin">Dan. 6.26.</note> And that is, that in all the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this her Maieſties Kingdome, all men of what eſtate and condition ſoever they be, tremble feare before the God of Queen Elizabeth, becauſe he is the living God which remayneth for ever, &amp; his kingdome ſhall not periſh, his Dominion ſhalbe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3307:16"/>everlaſting; &amp; that whoſoever ſhall wilfully and wittinglie ſpeake any blaſphemy, (much more, if they ſhall preſume to take ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour againſt him as this gaineſaying generation now doth) ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be drawen in pieces, and their houſes be made a ſinck. Know my Lords, that if you ſhall do otherwiſe theſe heathen Kinges will accuſe you in the day of the Lord: and take heed that none of your actes &amp; ſtatutes be found written with the bloud of the Saintes. For great Babylon &amp; her warriours, <hi>Corah</hi> and his main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teiners, ſhall come to remembrance, &amp; the Lord wil reward them according unto their deedes.</p>
            <p>And as in the former reſpectes I call your Honours to record with mee, ſo alſo herein I beſeech you to teſtifie the trueth on my behalfe, that I make an utter ſeparation betweene her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Civill Authoritie and the Eccleſiaſticall juriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe <hi>Corahs,</hi> theſe <hi>Dathans,</hi> theſe <hi>Abirams.</hi> The which I ſet downe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee can no ſooner account the falſe Miniſterie of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church to be Antichriſtian as it is, but evill diſpoſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcionable men wilbe readie to ſelander us that we account her MAIESTIES authoritie to be ſo too: as though her Majeſties power were eccleſiaſticall and not civil, or that this Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh band were Princes by their authoritie. What kinges and Princes do eſtabliſh is one thing, their Authoritie &amp; power wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they do this, is another. They may of overſight or otherwiſe ſet up the power of Satan by mainteyning falſe religion, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ordinances <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet their Power, that is, their Civill Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority whereby, they do this, is the Ordinance of God, though herein they highlie abuſe the ſame, and ſhall anſwere for it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their repentance.</p>
            <p>Her majeſtie, &amp; this high Court of Parliament, hath hitherto eſtabliſhed this Eccleſiaſticall regiment of the Kingdome of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, &amp; this band of Conſpiratours againſt the Majeſtie of Ieſus Chriſt, but this Conſpiracie is one thing, the authoritie whereby the ſame is eſtabliſhed is another. The Conſpiracie &amp; the Offices ther of are wholy from Satan, from the Dragon, from the beaſt, from the falſe prophet, out of whole mouthes theſe frogges iſſued; and ſo to be rejected. The Civill authoritie of her MAIESTIE and the Parliament wherby this treacherie (of overſight I truſt) is upheld, is the holy ordinance of GOD,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3307:17"/>(notwithſtanding it faileth herein) and therefore to be embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, to be obeied, and had in reverence: yet are they betimes to redreſſe the abuſe, before the Lord breake forth upon us in his wrath.</p>
            <p>And the Ordinances of Antichriſt eſtabliſhed by the lawful civill authoritie, do yet continue Antichriſtian and unlawfull. Becauſe falſe religion, and falſe ordinances Reteine their Nature by what power ſoever they be eſtabliſhed. The breach of Gods Law is the ſame by whom ſoever it be countenanced, enacted, commanded. The ſtatutes of Omry, the maner of the houſe of Ahab, the Damaſcene Altar, are ſtill Idolatrous monuments and conſtitutions, by whomſoever they be enacted, though by Ezekiah, Ioſiah, or by any other the Godly Princes of Iudah. And therefore the pretence which ſome alledge, contrary (I feare me) to the light of their owne knowledge, to cover their ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion unto the forenamed Antichriſtian ordinances; that Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, and Biſhops, Chancellors, Commiſſaries <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which her Majeſties Lawes do allowe, are become civill conſtitutions and not eccleſiaſticall, is altogither vaine and frivolous.</p>
            <p>For firſt no part of Poperie was ever impoſed upon us to be received of any the ſubjects of this Land, but what her Majeſties Predeceſſors the Kinges and Princes of this Land did by Law e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nact among their Subjectes.</p>
            <p>Againe, her Majeſtie doth eſtabliſh this as an eccleſiaſticall power, and not as any civill. Thirdly being an Antichriſtian Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution in it ſelfe, the power of man enacting the ſame cannot make it to be otherwiſe. Breifely, Maſſe, or any their Heathen Ordinances being enacted by Civil authoritie may by this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be frequented alſo, as being a civil thing, and not any Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian ordinance. And therefore men cannot better them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by this iugling.</p>
            <p>This whol Antichriſtian band in the time of Poperie, did not onely withſtand Ieſus Chriſt in the poinct of the outward offices, being the extremitie of <hi>Corahs</hi> ſinne, but alſo denied him the preferment to lodge any wiſe in the heartes of any men within
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3307:17"/>theſe Tentes. Nay theſe Tentes in thoſe daies were nothing elſe but a receptacle of all the inventions which Satan could deviſe for the diſhonour of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>In conſideration whereof, her Majeſtie, and the ſtate thought they had done well that they emptied thoſe tentes of the greateſt part of the fearfull ab hominations remayning in them, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threwe ſome of them, as the Papacie, the Cardinalſhip, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and planted the moſt of the veſſels of the houſe of God, that is the greateſt part of the doctrine of the truth in them: but the Tents and the Conſpiracie ſtill remaine in as direct a ſort againſt the glorie of God as that of <hi>Corah</hi> was; Nay by all this clenſing &amp; emptying (although we unfeighnedly praiſe our God for the ſame, and confeſſe it to have been a great worke) they have not as yet brought them into that puritie, and that ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Religion, that the Tents of <hi>Corah</hi> were in, as it will eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie appeare unto any that will conſider, that <hi>Corah</hi> ſtrove with Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes but touching the Office of the Prieſthood onely, whereas theſe men overthrowe the whole face of the Church of Chriſt, perſecute the Truth, and maintayne publikly many horrible ſinnes (whereat <hi>Corah</hi> would have bluſhed,) as the Idoll-preiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, non-reſidencie, the deſcending of Chriſt into Hell after he gave up the ghoſt upon the Croſſe, and had ſaid <hi>All was finiſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But touching the Authoritie of the civill power and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly of her right excellent Majeſty; I am in this place, for the ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of all ſclaunderous mouthes, who have or would report o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe of me, inforced to ſet downe what I hold and beleeve according to the word of God.</p>
            <p>I do therefore here acknowledge her Mejeſties Sovereigntie and regall Authoritie to be the Ordinance of the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, whereunto all perſons without exceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> within her Realmes and Dominions are to be ſubject &amp; to yeeld obedience in the Lord, not only for feare of puniſhment, but even for conſcience ſake, becauſe her forenamed authoritie &amp; power, is derived from the King of Kings, even the Lord Ieſus, who hath all power in heaven and earth in his owne handes.</p>
            <p>I doe alſo avouch that no forreigne power, Prince, potentate,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3307:18"/>or ſtate hath, or poſſiblie can have, any authoritie, within the Territories of her dominions, over any perſon, or in any cauſe, ſave onely what by ſpecial graunt he deriveth from her, and her Roiall Lawes.</p>
            <p>Her foreſaid authoritie I acknowledge to ſtretch it ſelfe, not onely ever all perſons, within her Dominions, but alſo over all cauſes as wel eccleſiaſtical as civil in ſuch ſort, as nothing is to be eſtabliſhed among her ſubiects, either in eccleſiaſticall or civil cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, publikl, or privately, but what belongeth vnto her power to correct, order, &amp; enact according vnto the written word of God, and the rules of common equide and iuſtice. So that, it doth no whit infringe her royal power and authoritie, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that ſhe hath any warrant, any power, any ſword, granted her of God to eſtabliſh either falſe Religion, falſe &amp; Antichriſtian or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, or yet any other vnwarrantable, or vniuſt conſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>Yet, if of overſight ſhe hath impoſed any ſuch thing vpon her ſubiects, and inflicted a penaltie vpon them for not obeying that wherto they cannot yeeld any ſubmiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without the breach of Gods lawe, I hold it to be the duty of private men to ſuller pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently the ſtroke of her ſword, and in no wiſe to withſtand the power thereof, either by open force, or ſecret practiſes, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to betake themſelves and their cauſe vnto the Lord God, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſiring him, to paſſe by her overſight, and to encline her heart and hand to embrace and mainteyue his truth, and to ſuppreſſe all falſhood, violence, and oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>Now if her Maieſtie and this high Court, require of vs that we reſort vnto the publick aſſemblies of the land, and ſo to enter (as hath ben ſhewed) into the tents of the Antichriſtian band, &amp; continue therein: I anſwer againe, that this is againſt the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word of God, and therfore that her Maieſtie hath no power, no authoritie from the Lord to require this at our hands. We are puniſhed for it: we anſwer againe that the ſword is given for our wealth, and not for our hurt, that it ought not to be drawen againſt vs for well doing: yet we paciently, and quietly bear the ſtroke, we dare not reſiſt, we dare not rebel againſt the Powers; Nay, we intreat our God day and night for the proſperity of her Maieſties crowne, deſiring him in mercy to paſſe by this blemiſh of her government, and not to lay it to her charge; earneſtly cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that her eyes and the eyes of your Honours may be opened
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3307:18"/>to ſee our innocency, and the truth wherein we ſtand, admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing both Her, and you, that although we for our parts knowe our ſelves bound even in nature to pacifie the hard dealing of our Prince and country towards vs by ſuffring, and bearing of their iniuries, as we would do our parents, that yet the Lord God who iudgeth without reſpect of perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, is an avenger of al ſuch things.</p>
            <p>In reſpect wherof, we dare notbut endeavour to the uttermoſt of our power to pull her and you from this conſuming fire of his judgements that hang over your heads even for the maintenance of this Antichriſtian merchandiſe within this Land, much more for purſuing vs, that will not trafique and intermedle with the ſaid wares.</p>
            <p>Hitherto I have ſhewed the Pariſh-aſſemblies of the Land, to be of a moſt feareful conſpiracie, againſt Ieſus Chriſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be diſſolved by your Honours, and avoided in the meane time, by all the Servants of Chriſt. But I would this prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, that theſe forreigne Romiſh Captaines have over them, were the only thing which maketh them vnclean vnto the Saints of God. Their caſe in the next place then is now to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, for the vnderſtading wherof I am to ſet down theſe grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds following.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That as the Lord hath appointed his word and trueth to be taught, his Sacraments to be adminiſtred, and the holy Order appointed by himſelf to be kept in his houſe and body; ſo he hath ordeyned a Power and authoritie, that is, certaine offices, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue whereof theſe things are to be done.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Next, that Chriſt Ieſus, being the head of his Church, hath ill fulnes of power, preheminence &amp; authority dwelling in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in ſuch ſort as his body and ſpouſe is to ſubmit her ſelf unto no power in religion ſave onely vnto that power which is derived from him that is her head. So that, as the Church is to receive no doctrines, no ſacraments, no order, but what the Lord hath an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be in his houſe; ſo alſo hee hath forbidden his ſaid Church to receive &amp; be ſubiect vnto any power &amp; authority ſave onely unto the power which is derived fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the head therof. For it is no leſſe derogatory vnto the Majeſty of Chriſt Ieſus for the Church to ſubmit her ſelf vnto the power of another head, though conveighing the truth with it, then to receive the falſe doctrines and falſe ſacraments of ſome other Religion or God.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:3307:19"/>3. Thirdly, that Satan in bringing the myſterie of iniquity to light, and in advancing the ſonne of perdition into his chaire of peſtilence, did not onely appoint falſe Sacraments, falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but alſo a falſe head, and a falſe power, that is, falſe Offices, by vertue wherof, both thoſe things were to be done, as alſo the Lords true inſtitutions and ordinances were to be violated in the Antichriſtian Synagogue.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That thoſe who preach the truth, adminiſter the ſacraments of baptiſme, and the Lords ſupper, and none other, by vertue of any of the falſe offices invented and reteyned in the kingdome of the Romane Antichriſt, derive their power wherby they doe theſe things from Antichriſt and not from Chriſt Ieſus. And therfore that ſuch working by vertue of a falſe power is not to be received of the church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now to come to the Pariſh-aſſemblies of this land, admit that <hi>ARCH BISHOPS, LORD BISHOPS &amp;c.</hi> bare no ſuch rule &amp; authority over them as now they do, and that there were none but Preachers in them, yet we demaund of theſe Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers by what authoritie they preach, baptize <hi>&amp;c,</hi> that is, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand what office they have ſo to do? whether this office of theirs be an office derived fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chirſt Ieſus, or a power left here by An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt. I ſay, that whatſoever they do, they doe the ſame by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of an Antichriſtian power, office, and calling, &amp; none other, That is, they do it either as they are Deacons, Preiſts, or as having a priviledged immunitie, licence, and diſpenſation countervey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a Deaconry or a Preiſthood. I adde this priviledged Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, becauſe ſome one among ten thouſand (it may be) being neither Preiſt nor Deacon, by vertue of a Licenſe from his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie doth ſerve a cure. Yet (if there be any ſuch) they are not capable of any charge, and what they do, they do it by this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the beaſt. And here becauſe I deale in a matter of fact, I call but day light, and common ſenſe to decide this whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie which is conteyned in theſe two points.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Whether at the expelling of the Pope out of this Land, by her Maiesties ſaves, the Popiſh offices of Preists and Deacons were expelled
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3307:19"/>alſo out of the Pariſh-aſſemblies, or reteyned?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Whether at the ſame tyme, or ſithence, any of the true offices of the Church of Chriſt, were instituted and ordeyned in the Pariſh-aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of the Land?</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The caſe is cleere, that the Popiſh offices, of Preiſts and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons were reteyned, and that the offices of Chriſts kingdome were not reſtored. And it is by vertue of the Popiſh offices of the Preiſthood, and Deaconrie, that the whole worſhip of God is performed, or rather polluted, and prophaned in all the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of this Land: for the proofe whereof, I call not onelie her Majeſtie, her lawes, and this high Court of Parliament to witnes, but alſo the cheifeſt mainteiners of the pariſh-Aſſemblies, namely, the forwardeſt Preachers of the Land, who in times paſt confeſſed (whatſoever they do now) that the offices of Chriſt were not planted, and therefore laboured to her Majeſtie, and the Parlement to have them eſtabliſhed in the pariſh aſſemblies.</p>
            <p>In regard of her Majeſties lawes, the caſe is cleere, that the State then being led by the ſight of our fathers in king <hi>Edwards</hi> daies, accounted the popiſh Church to be the Church of Chriſt, though corrupt, popiſh offices of Biſhops, Preiſtes, and Deacons to be the offices of the Church of Chriſt, and therfore retained them, for ſo we find it ſet downe in the booke of ordering Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Preiſtes made in King <hi>Edwardes</hi> time, and eſtabliſhed by her Majeſtes Lawes, as the ground &amp; rule whence, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the which all the Miniſteriall offices of the pariſh mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, yea of the whole Land muſt be ſquared. The book ſaith,</p>
            <p>That it is evident to all men diligentlie reading the holie Scripture, and the auncient authors,<note place="margin">In the Preface.</note> that from the Apoſtles time there have bene theſe orders of Miniſters in the Church of Chriſt, Biſhops, Preiſtes, &amp; Deacons. And therfore (ſaith the booke) to the intent that theſe orders ſhould be ſtil continued, reverent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie uſed, &amp; eſteemedin the Church of England it is requiſite that no man (not being at that preſent, Biſhop, Preiſt, or Deacon) ſhould execute any of them, except he be tried, examined, &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, according to this booke.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:3307:20"/>Again, no man in this Land can take a ſpirituall living, either Parſonage, Vicarage, Curatſhip, but by vertue of this Preiſthood, Deaconrie, or a Popiſh licence equivalent unto this Preiſthood, ſo that if a Preacher be beneficed, the ſame day that he denieth his licence, his Preiſthood, his Deaconrie, is he alſo deprived <hi>ipſo facto</hi> if it pleaſe his Ordinarie, and another may preſentlie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh himſelfe into his living if it were worth millions of gold. Nay whoſoever he be that wil caſt of theſe Popiſh orders, he is but a meere lay or private man, and ſo not capable of anie office in anie of the aſſemblies of this land: for ſo her Majeſties lawes, to wit, the foreſaid book doth conclude, that theſe offices were evermore had in that reverend eſtimation that no man by his owne private authoritie might preſume to execute any of them, and conſequentlie, that all men ſhould be called to the order of the Preiſthood, Deaconrie, Prelacie, according as this book doth allow. He that is made a Miniſter in ſom reformed Church beyond the Seas, is not capable of the Cure of a pariſh aſſemblie in this land, except he ſhall receive a Deaconrie, &amp; a Preiſthood after the order of our land, and yet he that receiveth orders in Rome is correſpondent, and anſwerable unto the pattern of our Deaconrie and Preiſthood, and ſo capable to buy &amp; ſel, that is, to execute any publike function.</p>
            <p>They are knowen caſes, that he who received his Preiſthood or Deaconry in King <hi>Henrie</hi> the 8 his dayes, is a Preiſt &amp; a Deacon under King <hi>Edward,</hi> Queene <hi>Marie,</hi> &amp; Queene <hi>Eliſabeth,</hi> by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the ſame orders, and he preacheth (if he can preach) being licenſed therunto, in King <hi>Henrie,</hi> King <hi>Edward,</hi> Queen <hi>Marie,</hi> &amp; Queen <hi>Eliſabeth</hi> their daies, by vertue of the ſame Preiſthood: for the office is the ſame, as both the booke, and everie man for the moſt part, doth account it. He that hath received but <hi>primam tonſuram,</hi> in King <hi>Henrie</hi> the VIII. or Queen <hi>Maries</hi> daies, being the firſt ſtepp of this abhominable order, may by lawe performe thoſe things under her Majeſtie which no lay man (as they call him) muſt preſume to take in hand. This caſe being cleer &amp; appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, if it be now demaunded, why wee will not heare the truth
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3307:20"/>taught by the preachers of the land, why we wil not receive the Sacramentes at their hands, we anſwere, that this we refuſe to do, becauſe we muſt not ſubmit or conſciences, our ſoules and bodies, being the temples of the holy Ghoſt, to be wrought upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to be ſat in, unto any power in religion, ſave only unto the power which is derived from our head Ieſus Chriſt: We anſwer that our head and Maiſter having all power dwelling in him, hath this peculiar intereſt in vs being his members, that he onely muſt ſit in our Conſciences by his ordinances. This intereſt of his he will not communicate with any creature, and therefore wee dare not though we ſhould ſuffer a thouſand deathes, to transferre the ſame unto anie, ſave unto himſelfe alone, and to joine with the popiſh aſſemblies of the Land. If the preachers do ſeeke <hi>I E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> and his honour by their preaching, they wil begin firſt with a lawful calling and office, they wil derive their power from him by vertue of the offices that he ordeined in his word. When they ſhall do this, &amp; walk according to the doctrine which is according unto godlines, wee will be the moſt willing to joine with them, the moſt glad to hear them, and to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with them, &amp; everie way to reverence them as the Miniſters of Ieſus Chriſt. In the meane time, let them not wonder that we hold this for undoubted truth, namely,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That whoſoever he be that ſitteth in the temple of God, that is, worketh upon the conſciences of men, by vertue of an Antichristian power, office, and calling, he is an Antichriſtian Minister, whatſoever truth he bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The trueth which ſuch Miniſters do teach, is but the bait whereby Satan in his myſticall deluſion &amp; powerfull ſubtilties hideth the falſe power, by meanes whereof hee in his ordinances ruleth over thoſe that otherwiſe would yeeld him no ſubjection, none obedience. When he cannot utter his ordinances by falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, he is glad to make them awaie by meanes of the truth.</p>
            <p>And he ruleth in the conſciences of men, not onely by falſe doctrine, but alſo by his falſe power and ordinances. His king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of darknes conſiſteth not onelie in the lies, and falſe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3307:21"/>and worſhip which he hath coined, but alſo in the falſe and Antichriſtian ordinances which he hath invented for the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his Idolatrous denne. And therefore the children and Saintes of God avoyd both the one, and the other. We owe him none obedience in either of them: and farre be it, even farre be it, I ſay, that we ſhould ſinne ſo treacherouſlie againſt our Lord &amp; Maiſter, and ſo greivouſlie againſt our owne ſoules to be ſubject unto Satan in either of them, ſeing by the moſt precious bloud of Chriſt Ieſus, and by the power of his croſse and reſurrection we have bene ſet free from all ſpirituall bondage whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Satan could not reigne in this land, by theſe his forenamed ordinances, if he brought not truth with him, &amp; it is no marveil that he bringeth trueth unto us, rather then loſe his kingdome. He can tranſforme himſelfe we knovve into an Angell of light, but vve muſt not receiv him or his mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſe, vvhat glaſſe ſoever he caſteth over them; or in vvhat vveed ſoever he cloth himſelfe.</p>
            <p>And therefore let it not be thought vvonderful, that vve reject that preaching, thoſe Sacraments, and thoſe Miniſters, that by their preaching, miniſterie, and ſacraments vvould dravve our conſciences to be ſubject unto the povver of Satan.</p>
            <p>Nay rather vve may vvonder vvith aſtoniſhment hovv they dare preſume to miniſter before Ieſus Chriſt, in the garments, vveeds, and offices of the Locuſtes of the bottomles pit: hovv they dare preſſe to offer before the God of Iſrael, being ſtrangers from the Tabernacle by vertue of their office. It vvas a poſitive lavv under Moſes, that the ſtranger not being of the line of Aaron, yea, or not called to the holie office, that vvould intermedle vvith the office of the Preiſt, ſhould dy the death for it. Much more if he vvere an Eckronitiſh or an Aſhdodean Preiſt in his office. And is not this man vvorthie of more honour then Moſes? his ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be yet more reverenced then Moſes his vvere? Oh then vvhat a fearful preſumption is it for the Preachers of this land (I ſpeak nothing all this vvhile of the Idol-readers, the Prelates, the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſaries, the Chancellors, the Deanes, the Archdeacons <hi>&amp;c</hi>) to take his vvord in their mouthes, his Sacramentes in their
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3307:21"/>hands, &amp; to miniſter in his ſight being not Aſhdodeans, or Eck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronitiſh, but Antichriſtian Preiſts (which is more horrible) by vertue of their office &amp; calling.</p>
            <p>The ſenſible preſidents of Gods fearefull iudgements upon Corah, and the two hundred &amp; fiftie Captaynes of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation (being men that held and taught (ſuch of them as were teachers) as many points of truth, as our preachers can hold or teach, time &amp; time being counted together. The fretting &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming leproſie of K. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> are written for their inſtruction &amp; ours, that they ſhould not preſume to intermedle with the holy things of God, eſpecially by vertue of a falſe &amp; Antichriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> office.</p>
            <p>If it be here ſaid that we have nothing to do what office they have, ſo they preach the truth, I anſwer that this is it which Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan would have, to wit, that his ordinances, his power, his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, ſhould be received of vs without any ſcruple or doubt what we do therby. Graunt him this once, and he wil ſoon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow all religion. I have ſhewed before, that a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will beginne with a lawfull calling and office, eſpecially in this holy work; and therfore if men have not forgotten to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, let them not uſe this graceleſſe uncolourable ſhift any longer to iuſtifie their uneven walking. For if their outvvard office and calling wil not abide the fire of the word, they are but wolves and vſurpers whoſoever they be. And if they be aſhamed or think themſelves too good to derive their office, authoritie, and power from Ieſus Chriſt, the Church of Chriſt and every member therof ought to be aſhamed and afraid to receive them; Nay the Church cannot receive them, without high treaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the head thereof Chriſt Ieſus, vnto whoſe power alone we muſt ſubmit our ſelves, for we have none other head but him, and therfore wil acknowledge no other power but his to have authoritie to work vpon our conſciences.</p>
            <p>They know what penaltie was to be executed vpon him under Moſes, that ſpake in the name of other Gods unto that people: how dare they then go about to thruſt us away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord our
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3307:22"/>God who hath redeemed us from the power of the grave, and to bring us into ſubjection unto the ordinances of that godleſſe <hi>Mauzzim?</hi> Do they not know, that, that Chriſt is not a true Chriſt but an Antichriſt whatſoever truth he teacheth, whatſoever mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles he worketh, which cannot prove his outward office and calling unto us out of the written word of God? What Miniſters then can they be but Antichriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe office &amp; calling cannot derive the genealogie therof out of the ſame booke of the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten undoubted veritie?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Christ Ieſus</hi> telleth us that the Scriptures are they which teſtifie of him, that his power even to preach; and not his preaching onelie, is, in the verie conſcience of his adverſaries from heaven and not from men; Hee tooke not the honour of his office unto him ſelfe, but he that ſaid unto him <hi>this day have I begotten thee,</hi> gave it him, as the Apoſtle teacheth. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> confirmeth his office out of the written word, namely, that he was that voice of him that crieth in the wildernes, whereof the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> had foretold the Church. The holy Apoſtles confirme their office out of the written word. For they wil not onelie prove that they preach nothing but the truth, adminiſter no ſacramentes ſave the true ſacramentes onely, but alſo wil ſhewe that they derive the power &amp; authority to do this from him who hath all power in his hand, that is from <hi>Ieſus;</hi> who did not onely inſtruct them what trueth the Church was to receive, but alſo gave them a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion to do the ſame from his owne mouth in ſaieng <hi>Go yee therefore &amp;c.</hi> Nay they durſt not preſume to chooſe any to ſupplie the roome of <hi>Iudas</hi> among them, except they had bene able to bring the warrant of the written word for their ground, that an office was void in the houſe of <hi>God,</hi> and that another was to ſupplie that roome. <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle is able to proue his office unto us out of many places of the written word. The Spirit of <hi>God</hi> teſtifieth that he is an Apoſtle of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> not at his own hand, but by the wil of <hi>God.</hi> What wil the Preachers of our time then ſay for them ſelves, why they ſhould not do the like? Many of them go about to deceive them ſelves &amp; the ſimple people by the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3307:22"/>place of Paul, <hi>Yee are the ſeale of mine Apostleſhip.</hi> We have called many (ſay they). But by vertue of what office, ſay wee. If they allege, we have nothing to do to examine that, truth, nay co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſenſe wil anſwere them, that then they are wicked intruders; that they are Lawleſſe theeves; that they are falſe Prophets; nay that they are Anabaptiſts, and that we may know them by this bitter preſumptuous fruite which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth out of their mouthes. For wil they preſume to take the word of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> in their mouths, to intermedle with his Sacramentes, to rule in his houſe; and wil they not ſhewe us how they come in, by what office they doe theſe things? wil they under pretenſe of an inward power, bragge of an outward office, nay exempt themſelves from the charge of of an office in the houſe of <hi>God,</hi> under the vaile of their outward giftes; and ſo breake into the ſame, in ſteed of entring in at the doore? Wee deteſt their Anabaptiſtrie. But to anſwer the word abuſed by them, <hi>Paul</hi> was an Apoſtle, and had his office thereunto, before ever he ſaw the Corinthians, yea, he had his office from <hi>Ieſus Christ</hi> before ever he preached. This office of his he proveth unto us by the written word, although he was in no wiſe to receive the ſame his office from the Church. Now if the Corinthians or any other whom he had called unto the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Goſpell ſhould by the inſtigation of the falſe Apoſtles call his office into queſtion, under the pretenſe that they knew not whether he ſpake true in affirming that Chriſt with his own mouth appointed him thereunto, becauſe he was not able to produce any witneſſes of this Commiſſion given as the reſt of the Apoſtles were; <hi>Paul</hi> anſwereth this, that they were an evident ſeale of his office; and as touching any calling from men, he was not to receive it. They were (I ſay) the ſeale of his Apoſtleſhip. For he was made conſpicuous amongſt them, by ſignes, by won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, by doing of miracles, They were by his Miniſterie indued with the giftes of healing, of miracles, of prophecie, of ſtrange tongues, and in theſe things inferiours unto no Church. So that although they would not beleeve his teſtimonie of him ſelfe, &amp; the witneſſe which <hi>Luke</hi> in the written word giveth of him;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3307:23"/>yet theſe moſt excellent, rare, &amp; ſupernaturall giftes wherewith he had furniſhed them, were a ſufficient ſeale unto their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences that he was the great Apoſtle of <hi>Ieſus Christ.</hi> Other witneſſes of his office was he to bring none, beſides his owne teſtimony warranted by the written word, &amp; the great power of the Spirit accompanying his Miniſterie in a powerfull ſort. For a calling unto this office of his by the Church was he to receive none.</p>
            <p>Now, are the Miniſters of our Pariſhes Apoſtles? When ſaw they <hi>Ieſus Christ</hi> then? when ſpake he with them? what miracle can they work, what ſtrange tongues which they ſtudied not can they ſpake? whom have they healed? whom have they indued with theſe rare giftes? why take they the polluted calling of the Preiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, or Deaconry from men? If they be not Apoſtles, they muſt not onely ſhew us their gifts, but alſo what office they have in the Church to execute the ſame. Thinke they to refuſe and caſt of the calling and order of <hi>God</hi> in his Church, by bragging of their operations? If they think themſelves bound to take an office of the Church, as their Preiſthood ſheweth they do, why will they not have us to turne over the booke of their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alogie, that we may ſee whether they be of that line of Aaron, or of the houſe of Corah? Whereas they bragge of calling and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the eies of any, I would learn whereto they have called them? to be Chriſtians? to the Church of Chriſt? they will not (I hope) ſay that the people were unchriſtianed Panims; that the Pariſhes were no Churches, before they came among them. Whence then have they called the people? out of the tentes of Corah? out of the kingdom of Antichriſt? why, both they &amp; their people continue their ſtill. And yf they ſay they have taught them many truethes, which they knew not; ſo may the Papiſt-prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers ſay too.</p>
            <p>And if they have furniſhed them with any of the giftes of the Spirit, they do thereby but deck and adorne a ſtrumpet in ſteed of the true ſpouſe of Chriſt, with the Iewel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the ſpouſe. And therefore if they wrought any knowledge in their people, let that be manifeſted by bringing them out of theſe Conſpiring Tentes,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3307:23"/>and preſenting them before the dore of the true tabernacle of Ieſus Chriſt. As to themſelves, if they wilbe the Miniſters of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, let them not fly the light, but prove their office out of the written word. For are they diſciples and wil they be greater then their Maiſter? Are they ſervantes, and wil they be greater then their Lord; Shal we yeeld unto them that lawleſſe unwrittn prerogative, which our head and Maiſter would not claime at our handes; nay which we durſt not yeeld unto him? that is, ſhall we receive them, having no warrant of the ſcripture, no Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from God to come unto us? They preach, they ſay, and they adminiſter the Sacraments: be it ſo. But we demaund of them by what power they do theſe thinges. If by a power, that is, by vertue of an Office comming from heaven, let them ſhew it as our Lord and maiſter Chriſt Ieſus did. If by a power co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming from men; or from the bottomleſſe pit; our Saviour Chriſt tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth us, nay even the book of Ordination &amp; her Majeſties Lawes tell us, that they are theeves and robbers, and they come unto us in the name and by the power of another <hi>God</hi> whome we know not &amp; will not acknowledge. And the Lord by his Prophet ſayth unto us with amighty voice, <hi>I have not ſent theſe Prophets, &amp; yet they ranne, I have not ſpoken unto them, and yet they Prophecie.</hi> They preach the trueth, they ſay, and adminiſter the ſacraments. Be it ſo; but have they taken the honour unto themſelves, or hath it ben given unto them by him who onely hath power to ſay, This day or at ſuch a time have I given thee honour &amp; holy office of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie in my Church?</p>
            <p>If they can name us the time &amp; ſhew us the office, we wil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve them, we will embrace them; otherwiſe we ſay unto them that <hi>no man taketh this honour unto himſelfe but he that is called of God as was Aaron,</hi> that is no man taking it, can have it; for many would take it, ſteal it <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if ſo they might come by the ſame. This folly, this preſumption, this colluſion ſhould not be heard of in Iſrael.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:3307:24"/>They preach, and baptiſe, they ſay. We demand who ſent them, who ſaid <hi>Go,</hi> unto them? If <hi>Ieſus Christ,</hi> let them ſhewe their commiſſion from him, that he hath ſaid unto them as he did to the Apoſtles, <hi>Go ye therfore</hi> &amp;c. If Antichriſt by vertue of an office in his body hath ſaid vnto them, Go ye therfore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they have power in deed to preach, and to adminiſter the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, unto ſuch as confeſſe themſelves to be under that head. But for our ſelves, we refuſe him and all his power, his members, his Officers. If Antichriſt ſaith vnto any, All power over the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of this Land is committed unto me, and becauſe many of the people would withdraw themſelves from my juriſdiction, if they had not the trueth taught vnto them, <hi>Goe ye therefore &amp; preach, that by meanes of your preaching, they may remaine within my Tentes:</hi> Shall we receive ſuch Preachers? <hi>God</hi> forbid. And yet ſuch are all the preachers of this Land. Shall Antichriſt ſay <hi>Goe,</hi> &amp; ſhall we ſay <hi>Come,</hi> vnto them? Shall they derive their power from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther head, then from <hi>Christ Ieſus,</hi> &amp; ſhall we be in ſubjecttion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them?</p>
            <p>They ſay, that they are the Miniſters of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> but we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand by whoſe will, by whoſe commaudement, by whoſe ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance? whether by the wil of God, by the commandement of God, by the ordinance of God; or by the wil, commandement, and ordinance of the man of ſinne that child of perdition? Their office which they have, the people over whom they are, the tents where they miniſter, the juriſdiction vnder which the ſubmit themſelves, the parties by whome, the place where, the time when, the ordinance wherby they are made, will eaſilie decide this controverſie, &amp; prove vnto their faces that they are limmes of that body in regard of their office (I ſpeak not of the mens perſons as touching the Lords election) which ſhalbe deſtroyed for evermore. And here it is to be obſerved, that when we ſpeak vnto theſe preachers of their office, they preſently runne to the execution therof, and prove themſelves to have an office, becauſe they performe thoſe things which apperteyne unto that office. As if an intruding Iudge or Iuſtice being demanded by her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3307:24"/>or her Counſaile, by what authoritie he ſat vpon the lives &amp; deathes of malefactors, by what authoritie he diſcharged out his warrants to call in and to reſtreine ryotous and vagrant perſons, ſhould anſwer, that he did nothing, but what was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoofull and needfull for the ſtate: which ſheweth not his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie power &amp; office whereby he intermedleth with theſe things, but rather giveth evidence againſt himſelfe, that he is a lawleſſe intruder, and ſo in danger of the penaltie of her lawes and her high diſpleaſure. The like is the courſe of theſe preachers.</p>
            <p>A ſtranger buſieth himſelfe in the Princes Court in thoſe thinges which are needfull to be done about the Princes roiall perſon, or otherwiſe. The Prince eſpieth him, and demaundeth who placed him in office, how he durſt preſume to come in preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, eſpecially ſo neere vnto the chaire of ſtate without ſpeciall leave and licenſe: The ſtranger anſwereth, that he doth nothing but what is meete, lawfull, and alloweable to be done, &amp; as for his office, the Prince is not to reſpect that, ſeing no evil is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, whatſoever it may be was purpoſed to be done, or how dangerous ſoever the preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent would be vnto the Princes roiall ſtate and perſon. And ſhall he be tolerated that preſumeth after this ſort againſt his Prince? queſtionleſſe no. Intollerable then, is their preſumption whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they be, who think that this manner of dealing will ſtand alloweable before the Prince of Princes. <hi>Offer it now vnto thy Prince</hi> (ſaith Malachie ſpeaking of any vnmeet ſervice) <hi>and ſee whether he will accept thereof.</hi> See whether a Prince wilbe content that he ſhould be attended vpon early and late, by no other officers then the knowen guard of the enemie; in the Liverie, and vnder the badge of the profeſſed enimie: no, no. For although theſe might for a time do ſome faithful ſervice, yet might the Prince be day and night in iuſt feare of trecherie, which at the length they would be aſſured to effect. Nay there were no reaſon (if they would ſerve the Prince) but they ſhould alſo caſt of the badge and liverie of his enemy, and conforme themſelves accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the will and direction, and be knowen by the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3307:25"/>cognizance of the Prince in whoſe ſervice they ſhould ſeeme to be imployed. We know the Prelacie, Preiſthood, and Deaconrie of old to have betrayed the glorie of God. We know that they were appointed for none other purpoſe then to diſhonour <hi>Ieſus Christ.</hi> Wee have late experience how trecherouſly they forſook the truth, and perſecuted the ſame after King <hi>Edwards</hi> dayes (wee ſpeak nothing of the preſent conſpiracie wherein they ſtand) And ſhould we now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit the ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſouls, the truth of God, the holy veſſels of the ſanctuarie, the watch and ward of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly city, unto ſo pernicious, faithles, and trecherous a genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which wilbe overthrowen whenſoever the Lord doth reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his, and cannot ſtand but by keeping him out of his right? If they meane to ſerve <hi>Ieſus Christ,</hi> let them enter into his houſe, and not continue in the pavilion of his enemy; let them caſt off their Antichriſtian cogniſance and office, and derive their office from him. In the mean time, let them learne that the office what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it be, &amp; the execution therof are ſo diſtinguiſhed and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red aſunder, that the one of them cannot poſſibly be the other. He may have a lawful office both in the Church and common wealth that never executed the ſame, as dying the ſame hower that he receiveth it, or otherwiſe. The Apoſtles had their office in the Mount, and ſo were true Officers by vertue therof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ever they executed their office, in preaching, baptiſing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if preaching and the adminiſtration of the ſacraments be the office of the Preachers of this Land, I marvel what they will have the execution of their office to bee. If preaching be their office, what Office have they when they preach not? What of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice have the dumbe Miniſters that cannot preach? The point is ſo groſſe and ſavoureth of ſuch groſſe ignorance, as it is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful that thoſe who are ready to object their want of learning vnto their adverſaries, and to claime intereſt in ſo large a porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof vnto themſelves, are not aſhamed of bewraying their weaknes in this ſort. For if preaching be their office, why are they Deacons, why are they Preiſts, why have they licenſes to preach? Why preach they not, when their Preiſthood, Deacon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3307:25"/>and Licenſes are gone? If preaching be their Office, what call they the execution therof, as I have ſaid? It will ſerve them in no ſtead to deny the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves to have the Popiſh Office of the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood or Deaconrie, in as much as they profeſſe more truths then wilbe profeſſedly tollerated in Poperie. Becauſe this confirmeth not their office, but the execution therof to be divers from that of the Popiſh preiſthood. The office of Biſhops, Preiſts, Deacons as hath bene ſaid, were not changed vnder her Maieſtie, becauſe they were thought to be the offices of the Church of <hi>Christ.</hi> The true offices were not reſtored for the ſame cauſe. And therfore common experience wil convince the vaine ſophiſtrie of men in going about to prove thoſe offices to be diverſe, which neither were altered, nor yet once thought to need any change or altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Nay, experience wil not onely teach us that our Preiſts have the ſame office with the popiſh ſacrificers, but alſo ſhew that they have many other things belonging vnt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them, which apperteyn unto none, ſave vnto the</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus much of the Copie I had, more of it I knew not where to have; whether it was finiſhed or not, before his death, I know not; for he was apprehended, adiudged, and executed, for witneſsing of the truth of Christ: (howſoever any other thing was pretended againſt him:) and (as I have heard) while he was about writing of this treatiſe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
